It was an age of war.
Relying on skill alone,
one man wandered the land.
A samurai.
KATSUURA, CHIBA PREFECTURE
This man is not
a wandering samurai of today.
I shouldn't have played the last game.
I visited my Go friend
for the first time...
after retiring.
I ended up staying late.
Damn!
Good, I made it in time.
Oh, no!
Kasumi, I'll let you borrow these.
What are they?
-Thanks.
-Read it.
I'll study these.
GO BEGINNER BASICS
-Study them.
-Sure.
I forgot them.
I'll go back.
No, I'll miss the last train.
Ah, I got a cramp!
Ouch!
Is that...?
A samurai.
After retiring, he lost his title
as a corporate man
and the support of his company.
Takeshi Kasumi, 60 years old.
This story
is about a normal 60-year-old man,
who is helped by a masterless samurai,
eating freely without being held back.
A gourmet fantasy.
MACKEREL IN THE MORNING
Mr. Samurai!
You forgot your change.
I must be drunk.
Thanks.
Don't mention it!
Hey, take it.
For bringing it to me.
-No, no. I can't.
-It's okay. Come on, take it.
Here.
Thank you very much.
Bye now.
-Mr. Samurai.
-What is it?
Why don't you stay
at my restaurant tonight?
No.
I appreciate the thought.
I'll just bed down wherever.
-But--
-Shelter from the night dew
is enough for me.
When the sun rises
I just go wherever I feel like.
Besides...
What a nice moon.
Clear skies tomorrow!
Ow, my back!
TOURIST
INFORMATION
Why should I hurry back home?
It's not like I have to go
to work tomorrow.
I WILL SEND THE BOOKS YOU LEFT
BY MAIL TOMORROW.
Hello?
Hello. It's me.
What happened?
I won't be home tonight.
Oh, really.
It means I'm staying out overnight.
Aren't you surprised?
I'm not surprised.
You're not a child.
That's true.
Anyway, that's it.
Okay. Then... goodnight.
Now that I think about it,
has he ever spent the night
away alone?
He hasn't...
Well...
Now to find some shelter
from the night dew.
GUEST HOUSE DAIKICHI
I slept well. Here we go.
I didn't see this when it was dark.
This area...
has a beach and is very lively.
Ah, that feels good!
-Good morning.
-Going out?
-Yes, for a walk.
-Take care.
-I'll be back.
Wandering around like this
without a plan...
isn't bad at all.
$10 PER POUND
That reminds me...
This is my first trip alone
in 60 years of living.
I just spent the night at an inn.
That's not really a trip.
But walking around
in a new area like this...
makes me feel like...
a wandering samurai.
A samurai...
would hold his chest out like this.
Time for a bath.
Taking a walk...
and taking a bath...
made me hungry.
All right.
That was good.
-Oh, welcome back.
-I'm back.
-Where did you go?
-To the market.
-Then you must be hungry.
-I'm starving.
Yes. I'll prepare breakfast now.
-Thanks.
-Please wait a moment.
What's for breakfast?
It's fish.
Yes.
Come in.
Excuse me.
-Good morning.
All right.
I'm here to serve your breakfast.
Here you are.
This is mackerel.
This is mackerel from Katsuura.
This is hijiki seaweed picked in Katsuura.
This is...
seaweed produced in Chiba.
Thank you.
-Thank you very much.
-Here.
-Excuse me. Enjoy your meal.
-Thank you.
I will.
A classic morning spread for an inn.
This is the best kind of breakfast.
Thanks for the meal.
Delicious!
The rice tastes different from at home.
Wasabi pickles.
I love the feeling through my nose.
Compared to my wife's cooking,
the flavors are pretty strong.
The food in places near the ocean
is a little salty.
I'll eat it with rice.
Natto tastes better the more you stir.
Breakfast at an inn isn't complete
without this.
Grilled to the perfect color.
This. This is it.
The taste of the sea.
The taste of life-giving Earth.
It tastes like the sea.
The taste of minerals that raised life.
It tastes like the sun.
The taste of the sun
that makes dried fish good.
And...
it tastes like fish.
The taste of life that swims
across the seas.
When I was a kid,
I didn't like fish.
I especially didn't like dried mackerel.
I started to like this taste...
Well...
one summer in high school.
Yeah!
The ocean!
What are you doing?!
My freshman summer break.
I went to an inn by the beach
with my friends.
Over there.
My first trip without adults.
Hey.
Over here.
Straight. Yeah!
Rock, paper, scissors!
It's so good!
Give me some!
Damn!
I lost!
I can't believe it.
The breakfast of that day...
was similar to the one today.
Here you go.
Thanks.
White rice and miso soup with clams.
Pickled cucumber and wakame seaweed.
Flavored nori,
pickled plums, and radish.
And...
dried mackerel.
Thanks for the meal.
This mackerel's amazing!
Really good!
Good!
What should I do?
I don't like dried mackerel.
It's really good!
You're so loud.
Because it's so good.
So good!
Yes.
That summer...
the dried mackerel I ate at the inn
tasted different from any mackerel
I'd ever had.
I remember that...
the more I chewed,
the more the taste filled my mouth.
Eating together
with my friends at the inn
must have made me hungrier.
And...
I was happy the woman
at the inn
didn't treat us like little kids.
Please eat as much as you like.
A young man's burning appetite.
I finished that small mackerel quickly
with the pickled plum,
seaweed, and pickled radish,
we ate a lot of rice.
Seconds!
-Me too, seconds!
-Me too!
-This is so good!
-It's really delicious!
I can eat five bowls.
-Then I can eat seven bowls.
-I can eat 10.
You said it!
-We'll take you up on that.
-Here you go.
-More, please.
-Yes.
Everyone ate three big bowls.
All the rice was gone in no time.
All right.
Thank you for the meal!
I'm so full!
I'm going to explode.
I learned to love mackerel that day.
A memory from many summers ago.
That memory...
makes this mackerel
even more delicious.
Should I get seconds?
No.
I'll get sick if I eat too much.
I'll stop here.
Excuse me.
Would you like seconds?
No.
-I'm fine.
-Okay.
I'm not like I was back in high school.
Hey.
-Here you are.
-Thanks.
Thank you for eating a lot.
Gotta eat enough in the morning
to be strong!
Excuse me.
May I have another?
-Here you are.
-Thank you.
So good.
It's good.
-Thanks for the meal.
-You're welcome.
-Thank you.
-Excuse me.
-Enjoy your stay.
-Thank you.
I ate a lot.
I'm so full.
I feel so full.
That was good.
Translated by:
Hoday Stearns